<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>More than conquerour a sermon preach't on the martyrdom of King Charles the I, Jan, 30, at Christ-church, Dublin : before his Excellency Arthur Earl of Essex, lord lieutenant general and general governour of the Kingdom of Ireland / by B.P.</title>
            <author>Parry, Benjamin, 1634-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31070</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11770888</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11770888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48853</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48853)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1490:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>More than conquerour a sermon preach't on the martyrdom of King Charles the I, Jan, 30, at Christ-church, Dublin : before his Excellency Arthur Earl of Essex, lord lieutenant general and general governour of the Kingdom of Ireland / by B.P.</title>
                  <author>Parry, Benjamin, 1634-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benjamin Tooke ..., and are to be sold by Joseph Wilde ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: B. Parry.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48853:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48853:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>More than Conquerour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach't on the MARTYRDOM OF King Charles the I.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. at CHRIST-CHURCH, <hi>Dublin,</hi> Before his <hi>Excellency:</hi> ARTHUR Earl of ESSEX, Lord Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and General Governour of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of IRELAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> B. P. <hi>D. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the KINGS Moſt Excellent Majeſty; And are to be Sold by <hi>Joſeph Wilde</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48853:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48853:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable and Excellent, ELIZABETH COUNTESS of ESSEX, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere not my <hi>obedience</hi> to your Ladyſhips Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, much <hi>greater</hi> than any <hi>ambition</hi> of <hi>being in Print,</hi> I ſhould not have troubled your Ladyſhip, or the
<pb facs="tcp:48853:3"/>
world, with ſo <hi>mean</hi> an Offering and performance; for which I ſhould, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Cuſtom, have made ſome <hi>ſolemn</hi> Apology, but that your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Patronage</hi> will be its <hi>beſt Vindication:</hi> a <hi>Favour,</hi> which as it <hi>tranſcends</hi> all that my merit or abilities in this kind can pretend to, ſo I cannot but be the more ſenſible of <hi>it,</hi> for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given me the honour (though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected) of paying my poor little loyal humble <hi>Mite</hi> to the never dying memory of the <hi>Beſt of</hi> KINGS; and thereby of publickly acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewiſe thoſe <hi>Obligations,</hi> and <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly</hi> the happineſs of attending his Excellency and your Ladyſhip, ſince my coming to this place, which ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes me in all gratitude and zeal</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Ladyſhips <hi>moſt devoted humble Servant and Oratour,</hi> B. PARRY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48853:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. VIII. xxxvii.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Nay, in all theſe things, we are more than Conquerours, through Him that loved <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are the <hi>Chriſtians Victory,</hi> the <hi>Believers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,</hi> his <hi>Tryals,</hi> and his <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs,</hi> his <hi>Outward Croſs,</hi> and his <hi>Inward Grace,</hi> his <hi>Temptations,</hi> and his <hi>Glory.</hi> Can there be any thing more <hi>bitter</hi> than <hi>Perſecution</hi> &amp; <hi>Famine,</hi> nakedneſs and diſtreſs, or more <hi>terrible</hi> and amazing than <hi>Peril,</hi> and the Sword. <hi>Skin for skin, and all that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48853:4"/>
a man hath, will he give for his life;</hi> and yet a good man will not ſtick to part with <hi>that</hi> too, when it ſhall pleaſe God to call for <hi>it,</hi> that he may haſten to his <hi>preſence,</hi> and be partaker of his <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> had run through a whole <hi>ſtage</hi> of miſeries, <hi>every Sermon</hi> he Preached, was turned into an <hi>Inditement</hi> againſt him, and afforded his malicious Perſecutors, <hi>freſh</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and matter to torment him with; he <hi>Travailed</hi> through as many <hi>misfortunes,</hi> as <hi>Countries,</hi> and found <hi>every place</hi> beſet with Thieves and Murderers to diſpatch him, no where <hi>ſafe</hi> almoſt, but in <hi>Priſon,</hi> fain to be guarded from one <hi>death</hi> to <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,</hi> from the <hi>fury</hi> of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> to the <hi>Roman</hi> Tribunal, and make his <hi>appeal</hi> from the rage of <hi>Zealots</hi> for Sanctuary to <hi>Nero. Shipwrack't</hi> by the <hi>Waves</hi> in one place, and the madneſs of the People in another, no where ſafe from Storms and Dangers, but made a <hi>Sufferer</hi> in <hi>every Element. Such</hi> was the condition of this <hi>Great Saint,</hi> who filled every place with his <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> the <hi>wonders</hi> of his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48853:4"/>
under all his Preſſures and <hi>Afflictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet it was no more, than what might juſtly be expected from thoſe <hi>migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> graces of the <hi>Spirit</hi> that ſtrengthned and adorned his Soul, that the World might ſee our <hi>Bleſſed Lord</hi> (when <hi>he aſcended up on high, and led Captivity Captive</hi>) took not <hi>away</hi> his <hi>Miracles</hi> and <hi>Graces,</hi> but left his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to <hi>continue</hi> and enlarge the <hi>wonders</hi> he hath done, to Propagate his Truth, and Inſtruct us for Heaven, <hi>That as many as through them ſhould believe in his name, might have power alſo to become the Sons of God, Heirs of the promiſe, and joynt Heirs with Chriſt, and more than Conquerours through him that loved them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>which words</hi> (not to inſiſt on that <hi>obvious Doctrine</hi> which ſprings from them, <hi>That croſſes and afflictions are the uſual lot and portion of the Righteous, and that all who live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution</hi>) I ſhall conſider theſe <hi>Two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</hi> 1. <hi>The power and excellency of Gods grace, goodneſs, and love, manifeſted in the faith, patience, and perſeverance of his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48853:5"/>
ſervants; their invincible courage and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in all their highest dangers and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and the infallible teſtimony and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he hath thereby given the World, of the Divinity of his Truth and Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The happy fruits, the victorious conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences and effects of this ſpiritual warfare, with the rewards and triumphs that attend it, in making us more than Conquerours, doubling and advancing our glory; heightning and augmenting our felicity and honour in this life, and that which is to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the <hi>Firſt, the excellency and power of Gods grace, goodneſs, and love, manifeſted in the faith, patience, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of his ſervants; their invincible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and reſolution in their higheſt dangers and temptations; and the infallible teſtimony and aſſurance he hath thereby given the world of the Divinity of his Truth and Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>periſhing</hi> a thing <hi>man</hi> is once left unto himſelf, without aſſiſtance from above, the whole Creation <hi>(which groans and travails to be delivered from the burden of our corruptions)</hi> ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48853:5"/>
the very ſenſe and conſideration of <hi>it</hi> extorted ſighs from the ſobereſt and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt <hi>heathens;</hi> and they have <hi>filled</hi> their Books with remonſtrances and complaints of the <hi>frailty</hi> and folly of their natures; the <hi>jarrs</hi> and diſcord of their <hi>own frames</hi> being <hi>greater</hi> than the <hi>wars</hi> of <hi>Elements;</hi> and more deſtructive to the Univerſe: the Contemplation of it turned one <hi>Philoſopher</hi> into an univerſal <hi>mourner,</hi> making his <hi>whole life</hi> one conſtant and continued <hi>Epitaph,</hi> weeping out his <hi>eyes</hi> and time at the <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and infirmities of mankind; and though they endeavoured with all the arguments of reaſon and wit to preſcribe a remedy for their <hi>misfortunes,</hi> yet they were too hard for themſelves, and found, That the ſtricteſt <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> the ſevereſt Diſcipline, and the higheſt <hi>Morality</hi> could never <hi>perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> reform or refine the <hi>man,</hi> ſo <hi>blind</hi> is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, and the very beſt of men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>aids</hi> and <hi>illuminatious</hi> of a <hi>divine light</hi> from above. Brag not then of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectualls, or thy parts; thy activity, or thy skill; thy old maxims, or thy new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48853:6"/>
thy fortunate reaches, or thy ſubtileſt incloſure; Let thy <hi>Anceſtours</hi> be <hi>dwarfs</hi> and <hi>pigmies</hi> to thy <hi>vaſter</hi> improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and the <hi>Anakims</hi> but <hi>ſhrubs</hi> and <hi>muſhromes</hi> to thy <hi>mighty</hi> productions; Let thy <hi>Cedar</hi> plantations outdo their <hi>quickset,</hi> and let them be but <hi>brambles</hi> to thy <hi>olive tree,</hi> and its <hi>fertile</hi> iſſues; Let the old <hi>Theatre</hi> and its <hi>pomp;</hi> the lofty <hi>Platonick,</hi> and the wandring <hi>Peripatetick</hi> bow down to our new <hi>Academies</hi> and Models, and <hi>exploded atoms</hi> be brought back with new <hi>pomp</hi> and ſplendour, to adorn the world, and make up its beauty. What are our <hi>Virtuoſo</hi>-triumphs, or their richeſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments and <hi>improvements</hi> without <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limer</hi> perfections in <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>virtue,</hi> but a <hi>golden dream,</hi> or glorious apparition; an elaborate <hi>ſhadow,</hi> or a ſtudied <hi>deluſion,</hi> and (which is far worſe) our <hi>damnation</hi> too. Nothing can <hi>truly</hi> chear the <hi>ſoul,</hi> or <hi>enliven</hi> the <hi>mind;</hi> advance our proſpect or our progreſs; give <hi>life</hi> or Sun-ſhine to our hopes and deſires; and enrich the heart with a <hi>ſolid,</hi> raviſhing, and <hi>unchangeable</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48853:6"/>
contentment and delight, <hi>above</hi> toyes and trifles; ſtorms or misfortunes, but <hi>divine love,</hi> and a victorious <hi>faith;</hi> a firm piety, and a conſtant devotion: <hi>theſe are</hi> the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of the world, the <hi>joy and glory of mankind,</hi> without which we had been <hi>ſtill in darkneſs</hi> and the ſhadow of death, heirs of ſin, and ſlaves to the Devil.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is indeed a <hi>higher</hi> act of <hi>omnipotence</hi> and <hi>love</hi> to <hi>reſtore</hi> the <hi>ſoul</hi> than the <hi>body;</hi> to <hi>redeem</hi> from <hi>hell</hi> than the <hi>grave;</hi> to <hi>rouz</hi> the <hi>ſinner</hi> than <hi>Lazarus</hi> from his tomb: a <hi>greater</hi> miracle of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and power to be <hi>renewed</hi> for <hi>Heaven,</hi> than <hi>awakened</hi> from our <hi>duſt;</hi> it coſt <hi>more</hi> to <hi>ranſome</hi> us from <hi>our ſelves</hi> and the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> and <hi>renew</hi> the <hi>divine</hi> image, than to make us <hi>live,</hi> or form us out of earth and nothing. But thus did God <hi>unlock</hi> his <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury,</hi> and <hi>display</hi> the <hi>riches</hi> of his grace, to let us fee, That as nothing is <hi>too</hi> great for his <hi>power:</hi> ſo nothing ſhould be too <hi>dear</hi> for his <hi>love; aſtoniſhing</hi> the <hi>heavens,</hi> and <hi>amazing</hi> the <hi>earth,</hi> and making the powers of hell <hi>ſhake</hi> at the <hi>wonders</hi> of our <hi>Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48853:7"/>
whilſt the <hi>Angels</hi> ſing, and the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphims</hi> renew their flames and brightneſs at <hi>our Converſion</hi> and glory, as if they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were made happier thereby.</p>
            <p>Stand ſtill ye <hi>Righteous</hi> and behold the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the <hi>Lord;</hi> the wonders and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of his Servants Piety through the World. The 11 <hi>chapter to the Hebrewes</hi> is a Catalogue of all the <hi>Worthies</hi> that lived and dyed in <hi>Faith,</hi> and the beginning of the next, is a Trumpet to Rouze us up to the ſame glory. <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, the onely ſolitary Saint of his time that converſed with Heaven by the purities of a tranſcendent Devotion, the firſt <hi>Hermit</hi> that went out of the way the common or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary road of the World to walk with God, and becauſe there was no fit compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for him on Earth (the World not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worthy of him) God was pleaſed to tranſlate him up alive to himſelf, that we might ſee what are the fruits of a <hi>Holy life,</hi> the rewards of Piety, and the raptures of Divine love. <hi>Noah</hi> was a <hi>Preacher</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and when they who regarded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48853:7"/>
not his Doctrine were buried with their Sins and Riots in ſilence together; God provided him a <hi>Sanctuary</hi> to preſerve his name and vertue, and perpetuate his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial with his Church for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abrahams Faith</hi> renewed his years, and made him fruitful in his poſterity as well as his Graces, he became the <hi>founder</hi> of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies and Kingdoms; but his nobleſt title of Honour was his being <hi>Father of the faithful,</hi> that was indeed a <hi>bleſſing</hi> which Crowns and Scepters could not give, he <hi>believed</hi> and it was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs, and that was <hi>Throne</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> enough; <hi>He ſtaggered not at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> and that eſtabliſht him for ever; he enjoyed his <hi>Maker</hi> here on earth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed ſo familiarly with heaven before he came there, that his very boſome hath been reckoned a place of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> ever ſince. Such is the priviledge and happineſs of the <hi>juſt</hi> who lives by Faith, he cannot dye even when he is breathleſs, for his life is hid with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> and being dead unto the world, he is alive unto <hi>God,</hi> and ſpeaks
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48853:8"/>
               <hi>eternity</hi> in his graces, he lives here by faith, a life of ſecret and inviſiible joyes; for, the life of nature is but a ſleep, and that of ſenſe a Dream; but that of grace is truly Vital, made up of the choiceſt Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and a never-dying compoſure. This is the life of a true <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and the greateſt glory of heaven upon earth, when we become conformable to the Death of <hi>Chriſt, Death hath no more dominion over us;</hi> but we can triumphantly, with our Apoſtle in another place, cry out, <hi>O Death, where is thy ſting? O Grave, where is thy Victory?</hi> A heart repleniſht with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine grace, is not eaſily frightned with <hi>ſtripes</hi> and <hi>impriſonment,</hi> hardſhip and want, peril or the ſword, or whatever elſe may ſcare a meer animal or Coward, but prepares to meet his <hi>God,</hi> in what way ſoever he ſhall be pleaſed to call him.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, it is no mean talent, no ſmall gift to bear our afflictions with a chearful and pious ſubmiſſion to God's will. It is not for every <hi>palat</hi> to endure the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48853:8"/>
of this Cup but his, that with <hi>David, hath taſted how good the Lord is,</hi> and that the end and <hi>fruits</hi> of his <hi>Croſs</hi> are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſs and peace. Storms and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are the tryals of a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> he that can endure theſe, and not be ſhaken or overthrown at <hi>Root,</hi> is ſit for Paradiſe and the regions of peace. To follow <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the <hi>loaves</hi> and <hi>miracles,</hi> in time of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and triumph, is no news: they that <hi>crucified</hi> him did ſo; but to keep him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in the <hi>deſart,</hi> or more formidable <hi>Garden,</hi> and not ſhrink at the approach of <hi>Lanthorn</hi> and <hi>Souldiers;</hi> the <hi>Traytor</hi> and the <hi>Trainband,</hi> a <hi>midnight</hi>-terrour, or an <hi>open</hi> diſtreſs. To fall when we are in our <hi>Spring,</hi> and be <hi>ſacrific'd</hi> in the pride and ſtrength of nature; to ſubmit to flames and Axes, and be <hi>tormented</hi> at every <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants</hi> pleaſure, to take up our heavieſt croſs, and thus dye for the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is a temper as Rare as it is Happy, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults of an invincible Piety and Faith, the higheſt ſtrength and glory of a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore Secondly, It is a mighty
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48853:9"/>
proof and argument of the <hi>Divinity</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> That the Doctrine of the <hi>Croſs</hi> ſhould find ſo many worſhipers and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; That men ſhould at firſt be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> onely to afflictions, and made <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate</hi> that they might ſuffer, grow in love with their perſecutions, and rejoyce in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than imitating the example of their <hi>Holy Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true we read of ſome <hi>Heathens,</hi> That brag'd of their Valour and Courage in the midſt of their <hi>misfortunes;</hi> that they had acquired a temper of being above ſtorms, and could defie lightning and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by <hi>Lawrels</hi> of their own making: and though nothing be more noble to Conquer our paſſions, and be armed againſt the Caſualties and Calamities of this <hi>World.</hi> Yet examples in this kind are very <hi>rare,</hi> few or none amongſt them have ever done it, for even the prowdeſt <hi>Stoicks,</hi> and they that ſpoke biggeſt of themſelves and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, were Cowards to their own Rules, and fainted under the flouriſh of their fine diſcourſes; and whatever their ſeeming bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48853:9"/>
might be; yet their <hi>hopes</hi> were va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing and ſhallow, neither ſatisfactory to the Soul, nor durable in themſelves; and though ſome of them are ſaid to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured <hi>death,</hi> rather than violate or falſifie their word and truſt, they are to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for ſo doing, and it is no error or miſtake to ſay, that <hi>God</hi> might Crown them with more ſtrength than ordinary, as well to <hi>juſtifie</hi> a good cauſe, as for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement even of moral <hi>vertue</hi> in this life: but yet theſe inſtances, and whatever elſe can be produced in this kind, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Liſt of <hi>diviner Heroes</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> the multitude of <hi>victorious Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> of every Age and Sex, who cannot poſſibly be thought owners of ſuch <hi>ſtrength</hi> of body and mind, as to endure the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to which they were expoſed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſecret <hi>arm,</hi> an inviſible <hi>power,</hi> and a mighty irreſiſtable <hi>grace</hi> ſubduing all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>if</hi> it ſhall be further urged, that even amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as Sectaries and others (if they may be called <hi>Chriſtians</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48853:10"/>
that are out of the Church) there are ſome ſo ſtout, that no <hi>penalties</hi> almoſt can force them to recant or renounce their <hi>errours,</hi> and return to their wits and duty again: we muſt ſay firſt, That they are few for the <hi>number,</hi> and much fewer for their <hi>worth.</hi> Secondly, That the <hi>obſtinacy</hi> of bad men in a bad cauſe, as it doth not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their crimes, ſo neither doth it diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the piety and virtue of good men in <hi>a good;</hi> for, a notorious <hi>Malefactour</hi> is not leſs a <hi>Criminal</hi> for being obſtinate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relenting, and therefore it does not at all diſparage or evacuate the power of <hi>Gods grace,</hi> that even wicked and carnal men may ſeem to have a ſhare ſometimes of the ſame <hi>fortitude</hi> and <hi>courage,</hi> for <hi>hypocriſie</hi> is no ſtranger in the World. The beſt things have their <hi>Counterfeits,</hi> and it is the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils</hi> conſtant work, and choiceſt <hi>maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece,</hi> to imitate as much as he can, the gifts and graces of <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf into an <hi>Angel of light</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude the <hi>World;</hi> but as no man in his witts will ſay, there is no ſuch thing as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48853:10"/>
               <hi>Truth,</hi> becauſe ſome have writ <hi>Fables</hi> and <hi>Romances;</hi> ſo neither can we deny the mighty <hi>operations</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> in his <hi>Church</hi> and Servants, becauſe there are ſo many <hi>lyars,</hi> and <hi>pretenders</hi> to the ſame Spirit: ſince we have a <hi>ſure</hi> rule left us, by which we are to <hi>walke</hi> our ſelves, and <hi>judge</hi> of others.</p>
            <p>In a word if it be true, That it is the <hi>cauſe</hi> alone which makes a <hi>Martyr,</hi> than they who have no <hi>other certificate</hi> from Heaven, but <hi>that</hi> which is common to <hi>Brutes</hi> alſo; are not <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Conquerours</hi> but <hi>Cheats</hi> and <hi>Deceivers,</hi> and they are <hi>Children</hi> in <hi>grace</hi> as well as <hi>knowledge,</hi> that will be thus <hi>baffled</hi> and <hi>trepann'd</hi> from their <hi>Holy faith,</hi> by ſuch <hi>Tricks</hi> and <hi>Impoſtures.</hi> There is no man living without his <hi>Croſs</hi> in this World one way or other; but he that <hi>bears</hi> it <hi>piouſly</hi> and bravely and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures to the end,</hi> he <hi>ſhall</hi> be <hi>ſaved,</hi> and he that <hi>ſuffers</hi> for <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> ſake is bleſſed for ever. <hi>What man is he that would ſee good dayes</hi> in ſpight of all his Enemies and Oppreſſors, <hi>keep thy Soul from evil,</hi> and thou
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48853:11"/>
ſhall be <hi>happy</hi> in the <hi>midſt</hi> of thy <hi>Troubles,</hi> and what ever the World may rob thee of; yet <hi>Heaven</hi> is thy <hi>portion,</hi> and its <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhments</hi> thy <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>reward,</hi> no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity can deprive thee of <hi>that,</hi> ſince the <hi>more</hi> thou art <hi>afflicted,</hi> the <hi>greater</hi> is thy <hi>Crown;</hi> and therefore no <hi>good Chriſtian</hi> will <hi>murmur</hi> or <hi>repine</hi> at the <hi>various</hi> methods of Gods providence in <hi>this</hi> World, that thus exerciſeth the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>patience</hi> of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that <hi>their joyes</hi> and <hi>his</hi> glory may be the <hi>greater.</hi> For what ever the frailty of our natures, and the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of fleſh and blood may be, he that <hi>ſincerely</hi> makes <hi>God</hi> his <hi>hope,</hi> ſhall not want a <hi>deliverance</hi> from, or Conſolation in his <hi>diſtreſs,</hi> which they that carnally and <hi>Sceptically</hi> deride, are not worthy to receive, which brings me to the next particular. <hi>The happy fruits, the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſequences and effects of this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al warfare, with the rewards and triumphs that attend it,</hi> in <hi>making us more than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours, Crowning us with peace, &amp; ſtrength, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt in this life, and eternal glory in the next.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48853:11"/>When God told St. <hi>Paul,</hi> That <hi>his grace was ſufficient for him,</hi> he triumphantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, He could <hi>do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengthened him;</hi> for having made it his conſtant exercize and ſtudy, <hi>to have alwayes a conſcience void of offence;</hi> he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the <hi>face</hi> of man, but thirſted to behold <hi>that</hi> of Gods, and could with more <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> lay <hi>down</hi> his <hi>life,</hi> than other men could <hi>preſerve theirs;</hi> ſo <hi>vaſt,</hi> ſo admirable a <hi>change</hi> can the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> make in the <hi>ſoul</hi> of man, with ſuch glory diſplay his <hi>Omnipotence</hi> in our <hi>weakneſs,</hi> His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in our <hi>infirmities,</hi> and make <hi>humane miſery</hi> and <hi>diſtreſs, a Theam</hi> and <hi>Theatre</hi> to <hi>diſplay</hi> the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>riches</hi> of his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Bleſſed Lord</hi> could have armed his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> with a word to have <hi>cruſh't</hi> the Earth to nothing, given them legions of Angels to prepare their way and gather Captives; or with ſtorms and lightning have <hi>blaſted</hi> the World into <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> and Homage, and made Kingdoms tremble and bow down before them. But he took <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48853:12"/>
courſe, which though not ſo <hi>outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> pompous, or <hi>ſeemingly</hi> powerful and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing; was yet more <hi>wonderfully</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly glorious</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsful;</hi> making <hi>weak things to confound the mighty, and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh things to confute the wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Babes</hi> and Children to diſarm <hi>Caeſars</hi> and their legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>baffle</hi> their <hi>ſtrength</hi> and their <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> together: and by humility and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, faith and perſeverance, <hi>gain more</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs then by Arms and Banners, teaching us thereby neither to <hi>truſt in,</hi> nor <hi>make uſe</hi> of an arm of <hi>fleſh</hi> in His <hi>ſervice,</hi> that His <hi>Goſpel</hi> was not to be <hi>propagated</hi> by <hi>violence</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> force or murder, <hi>Treaſon</hi> or Compulſion, but the <hi>nobler Warfare</hi> of <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi> Vindicating alſo his <hi>Providence</hi> by bringing good out of evil, defeating the malice of his Enemies, and the arts of the Devil; making good the <hi>Truth</hi> of his <hi>promiſes</hi> in the <hi>faith</hi> and courage of his <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> that his <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> was indeed the <hi>Comforter, the Lord and giver of life,</hi> both in the <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> and the <hi>exaltation,</hi> the <hi>exerciſe</hi> and <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48853:12"/>
of their <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>graces,</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>ſupporting</hi> and <hi>ſuſtaining</hi> their <hi>infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities;</hi> but by <hi>inſpiring</hi> them above all the horrours of <hi>Mortality; rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer for his name ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An honour <hi>greater</hi> (I may ſay) then that of <hi>Angels,</hi> who live, but not by <hi>dying,</hi> are Miniſters of his will, but not <hi>Martyrs</hi> for it; They <hi>ſtand before the Throne,</hi> but <hi>their voice</hi> is not heard from <hi>under</hi> the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> they afford not their <hi>Maker</hi> cauſe or occaſion to diſplay ſuch <hi>variety</hi> of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And therefore for man, <hi>frail man</hi> duſt and aſhes not to <hi>fear death,</hi> is more wonderful and glorious than to be <hi>above it,</hi> and to <hi>expire</hi> for Gods <hi>Truth</hi> more <hi>noble</hi> than their <hi>immortality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore our <hi>Holy Lord</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc't a <hi>double</hi> bleſſedneſs to them that <hi>ſuffer</hi> for Righteouſneſs ſake, the <hi>honour</hi> and the <hi>reward</hi> of perſecution; Their <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſacred</hi> and their <hi>name preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> their <hi>ſufferings eterniz'd,</hi> and their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>duſt immortal,</hi> and the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48853:13"/>
being their aſſured <hi>portion,</hi> they ſhall at the Reſurrection of the juſt, exchange their <hi>Purple</hi> for a <hi>Robe</hi> of <hi>light,</hi> and their <hi>Crimſon dye</hi> for a <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> and ſhine for ever, as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father.</p>
            <p>And truly were it not for this, what would the <hi>life of a Chriſtian be,</hi> but a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable</hi> and <hi>empty nothing?</hi> the <hi>puniſhment</hi> and <hi>deriſion</hi> of <hi>mankind?</hi> why did <hi>David</hi> complain that he was <hi>become a ſcorn to all that were round about him,</hi> he might have turned <hi>ſcorner himſelf,</hi> and inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Royal Prophet,</hi> have been a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> or an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> as <hi>proud</hi> and imperious, as the greateſt <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Barbarian Monarch.</hi> For a <hi>Prince to wiſh himſelf a door-keeper in the houſe of God,</hi> and be content to leave his Throne and Kingdom <hi>flowing with milk and honey</hi> for a <hi>new Jeruſalem,</hi> was a pleaſant <hi>Paradox</hi> for the Carnal and the <hi>prophane</hi> to <hi>droll at;</hi> And that the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> and their ſucceſſive <hi>Martyrs</hi> ſhould <hi>endure</hi> the <hi>ſcoffs,</hi> miſeries and torments of vulgar rage and madneſs, for an <hi>inviſible</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48853:13"/>
Kingdom, had they not the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions for <hi>proof</hi> and the <hi>higheſt</hi> conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for <hi>ſupport,</hi> might well be look't upon as the higheſt degree of <hi>folly</hi> in the world. And ſo no queſtion it appears to <hi>thoſe</hi> that are yet <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to their <hi>graces,</hi> and have not yet felt the <hi>leaſt ſpark</hi> of that Divine <hi>fire,</hi> which <hi>warmed</hi> them into <hi>flames</hi> and <hi>rapture;</hi> They that <hi>will not believe,</hi> ſhall never find nor know what the <hi>joyes</hi> and <hi>breathings</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> are, how <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>irreſiſtable</hi> its <hi>ſtrength,</hi> how <hi>ſweet</hi> its <hi>influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> how raviſhing its <hi>charms,</hi> how <hi>power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>divine</hi> its <hi>motions</hi> and its <hi>light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Infidels</hi> wit then grow <hi>big</hi> with his own <hi>folly,</hi> and ſtrain hard to make his <hi>nonſenſe faſhionable</hi> and taking, let the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt</hi> and the <hi>prophane</hi> ſit as <hi>dictator</hi> in his <hi>Chair,</hi> and be the founder of a <hi>new Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy,</hi> wherein to <hi>Apoſtatize</hi> or <hi>Blaſpheme,</hi> ſhall be no more a <hi>ſin</hi> but an <hi>improvement.</hi> Let the <hi>Temporizer</hi> and the <hi>Coward,</hi> the <hi>worldly</hi> mind and the <hi>falſe</hi> heart, <hi>follow</hi> the <hi>fortune</hi> and <hi>flatter</hi> the <hi>ſins</hi> of <hi>Tyrants;</hi> be <hi>Diſciples</hi> of a <hi>prevailing faction,</hi> and <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48853:14"/>
the <hi>crimes</hi> of <hi>proſperous</hi> impiety, count <hi>Treaſon</hi> no <hi>ſin,</hi> nor <hi>inconſtancy</hi> a <hi>ſhame, laugh</hi> at <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> and <hi>faſt</hi> with the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee,</hi> onely to <hi>whet</hi> their ſtomacks and be the <hi>more devouring,</hi> anoint their forehead with <hi>perjury,</hi> and make <hi>long prayers</hi> even to a deſolation. Let the <hi>levelling</hi> of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es be the <hi>Zealots</hi> pride, and the <hi>pulling down</hi> of Crowns and Scepters the <hi>Saints priviledge,</hi> let the <hi>vitious</hi> and the vile <hi>thrive</hi> and flouriſh for the <hi>time,</hi> grow <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure</hi> in all their <hi>worldly</hi> ends and <hi>enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> yet <hi>after all there is God that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Earth,</hi> and who beſides his <hi>venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance hereafter,</hi> can curſe the wicked in their <hi>Graves,</hi> when they ſeem to have <hi>eſcap't</hi> his <hi>anger,</hi> purſue their <hi>Carkaſes</hi> and <hi>Ruines,</hi> and make their very death but the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of a <hi>worſe</hi> deſtruction, plague their <hi>poſterity,</hi> and bring them alſo to an account for their <hi>predeceſſors crimes. Blood</hi> hath a <hi>crying</hi> and a <hi>peircing voice;</hi> it <hi>awakens</hi> the <hi>Dead</hi> and makes them ſpeak, nay, it reaches Heaven and will not let God alone, till he <hi>deſcend</hi> and <hi>revenge</hi> its <hi>cauſe,</hi> it was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48853:14"/>
fright and his prayer, That God would <hi>preſerve him from blood guiltyneſs,</hi> if he <hi>prayed</hi> ſo for <hi>himſelf,</hi> what muſt they do that <hi>murderd David.</hi> If the blood of Gods <hi>private</hi> Saints and Servants <hi>cry from under the Altar, That of his Anointed</hi> will peirce through ſure? and when the <hi>ſin</hi> ſeems <hi>ſpent</hi> or <hi>forgotten;</hi> yet the <hi>puniſhment is not,</hi> that may laſt and paſs from one <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to another,</hi> and even in <hi>this</hi> life as well as the <hi>next,</hi> God will make it appear, that ſooner or later, he will bring iniquity to remembrance, and avenge the blood of his <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>plague</hi> a <hi>guilty land</hi> with <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment</hi> and <hi>horrour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore it is the ſpecial <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>deſign</hi> of our preſent meeting this day, to <hi>ſilence,</hi> if we can, the <hi>voice</hi> of <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>Royal blood,</hi> by a <hi>repentance</hi> loud as our ſins, and alſo to reverence and renew the <hi>memory</hi> of a <hi>Prince, ſacred</hi> for his <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and his <hi>graces, bury him</hi> afreſh who can <hi>never</hi> dye; and whilſt his <hi>murderers</hi> (barbarous after death) denied him the Obſequies of a <hi>King,</hi> we will be his <hi>year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48853:15"/>
mourners,</hi> and interr him afreſh with a more illuſtrious ſorrow.</p>
            <p>And truly no Age or People almoſt ſince the <hi>Creation,</hi> ſtand more in need both of the preaching and the practice of <hi>true</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and obedience, than the ſinful Kingdoms in which we live; for none have ſo degenerated from the honour and beauty of <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> none have ſo affronted its <hi>Holy Authour,</hi> and diſgrac't his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed his <hi>Word,</hi> or perverted it more. For that very courſe and method which <hi>God</hi> at firſt appointed, and ſtill continues to the world to cure its confuſions, creating <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> to keep the Peace, and ſending <hi>Kings</hi> as his own <hi>Vice-gerents</hi> to heal our diſorders, and ſtrengthning the Bleſſing by commanding every ſoul, to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to their authority and power, that ſo we might the better learn to fear and obey him. We have employed to a quite contrary <hi>deſign,</hi> and as if we had never heard or learnt any ſuch <hi>Leſſon,</hi> by a new <hi>Divinity,</hi> will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>fear God, nor honour the King;</hi> for <hi>Monarchy,</hi> they ſay, is an arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48853:15"/>
not fit for <hi>Saints,</hi> that would rule all as <hi>Kings</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>Such is the <hi>end</hi> and <hi>fruit</hi> of all popular Tumults, preach't up under colour of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and <hi>Reformation;</hi> no noiſe louder, no quarrel finds more Seconds, than that of <hi>Religion,</hi> every man turns <hi>zealot</hi> in ſuch a cauſe, wherein he hopes his own <hi>Diana</hi> ſhall be <hi>uppermoſt,</hi> and his fortune advanc't by uſurping his Neighbours <hi>Vineyard</hi> for his inheritance; and accordingly they made it their buſineſs to cry out on the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> that they might get <hi>proſelytes</hi> for a faction, and exclaim againſt the <hi>Church,</hi> to gain <hi>Diſciples</hi> for a <hi>Reformation.</hi> Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to find fault, firſt with their <hi>Prince,</hi> and then as handſomely transferr it on his <hi>evil Counſellors,</hi> out of their <hi>loyal</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant affection abuſing him doubly. Firſt in his <hi>perſon,</hi> than in his <hi>choice,</hi> committing a double errour, firſt in making themſelves, both parties, Judges and Executioners, and ſecondly, In taking a wrong courſe, by making <hi>Rebellion</hi> a way to <hi>Reformation, Diſobedience</hi> a remedy for pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48853:16"/>
and redreſs at moſt but ſmall faults, by committing much more great and horrid: an <hi>Artifice</hi> ſo profoundly <hi>politick</hi> and <hi>Divine,</hi> that by it no <hi>perſon</hi> or <hi>calling</hi> ever can or ſhall be ſecure.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Pride</hi> and Ambition ſcorn all bounds of Juſtice or <hi>Duty,</hi> The new, the beſt and ſureſt way to ſubvert the Crown, was by taking away its <hi>Supporters;</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe two great <hi>Heroes</hi> and Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Church and State, the noble <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> (from whom the Reformation of <hi>this Church</hi> and Kingdom, derives the beſt part of its ſtrength and beauty;) and the pious <hi>Laud</hi> who thought nothing <hi>too great</hi> for <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> were by a <hi>new found ordinance,</hi> thought the <hi>fitteſt Sacrifice</hi> to prepare and lay the Scene of a <hi>deeper</hi> and more fatal <hi>Tragedy. Princes</hi> ſeldom fall <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, Crowns</hi> and <hi>Miters</hi> like Twins cannot well be parted; ſo great a Majeſty and vertue could not goe of a <hi>cheap</hi> and <hi>ſingle</hi> Sacrifice, but like a mighty <hi>Earthquake</hi> carry <hi>open ruine</hi> with it. And though his <hi>Murderers</hi> like themſelves denyed him the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48853:16"/>
Funerals of a <hi>King,</hi> they provided him a <hi>more ſolemn</hi> and illuſtrious <hi>attendance,</hi> ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſome</hi> that could not <hi>follow</hi> him to the Grave, to keep him <hi>Company</hi> in it, mingle ruines, and Crown his Triumphs with <hi>freſh</hi> Purple, out of their own veins. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>reſt</hi> of thoſe <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>Heroick perſons</hi> that <hi>bled</hi> for their <hi>Prince</hi> and Country, let <hi>His Name</hi> flouriſh and be Honourable in <hi>this Kingdom</hi> alſo, from whom (by His Majeſties goodneſs) we now derive and enjoy a <hi>Governour,</hi> under whoſe <hi>Pious influence</hi> and <hi>Prudent care,</hi> we may (by Gods bleſſing) reap as <hi>much good,</hi> as the <hi>Church</hi> hath <hi>glory by his Fathers ſufferings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is but a poor <hi>excuſe,</hi> and worſe amends after all, to tell us they never <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi> ſo <hi>fatal a change,</hi> for had they not <hi>taken away</hi> his <hi>power,</hi> he had never <hi>loſt his life.</hi> But where did we ever yet ſee <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults</hi> guided by <hi>diſcretion,</hi> or a Riotous <hi>multitude</hi> obſerve any <hi>bounds?</hi> Never was any <hi>Kingdom</hi> thus <hi>mended,</hi> that was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>ſubverted,</hi> and made a Sacrifice in its
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48853:17"/>
own flames: <hi>Rebellion</hi> having once got ground and footing, knowes <hi>no limits</hi> but its own <hi>Ruine,</hi> and as it began with the <hi>Devil</hi> firſt, ſo it ſeldom ſtops till it come to <hi>Hell.</hi> And therefore 'tis compared in Scripture to <hi>Witchcraft</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> becauſe it is the proper work of the <hi>Devil,</hi> and renders us like him. For <hi>Subjects</hi> to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne</hi> and <hi>murder</hi> their <hi>Prince,</hi> and with unheard of impudence pretending to Piety and Juſtice, <hi>condemn</hi> him who is <hi>the life of the law,</hi> and the <hi>faiths Defendor;</hi> is ſuch a piece of <hi>Religion,</hi> as the <hi>Devil</hi> never yet durſt preach to <hi>Infidels</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> 'tis a <hi>Prodigy</hi> in nature againſt the <hi>common notions of mankind, worſe</hi> than <hi>Brutes,</hi> for they ſtand in <hi>awe</hi> of their <hi>King,</hi> not more for the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of his <hi>limbs</hi> than the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of his <hi>temper:</hi> and does <hi>Religion</hi> (think you) command that which is <hi>deteſtable</hi> to every nature under the Sun? <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> ſure hath not made <hi>Kings</hi> more weak and deſpicable, nor was <hi>it</hi> planted to <hi>dethrone,</hi> but <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> them better.</p>
            <p>God never made <hi>Rebellion</hi> a <hi>grace,</hi> 'tis
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48853:17"/>
not to be found in the Catalogue of his <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>bleſſings,</hi> his Goſpel gives no ſuch Commiſſion, nor is <hi>violence</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> any part of its Doctrine or Diſcipline; The <hi>Sons of Belial</hi> are no fit <hi>pen-men</hi> for the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> nor does a <hi>Drum</hi> or <hi>Trumpet-lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> become the Pulpit. What ſhould I now lead you to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs Tombs, where</hi> nothing but <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>innocence</hi> are aſleep; you ſhall read or hear of no <hi>Treaſon</hi> in their <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> nothing to <hi>ſully</hi> the brightneſs and memory of their <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> they never <hi>wronged Caeſar</hi> when <hi>alive,</hi> and their <hi>deaths</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>them</hi> his <hi>beſt friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence then came the noiſe and tumult in our ears? Where did we learn the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>mutiny</hi> of <hi>ſchiſm</hi> and <hi>ſedition,</hi> of <hi>pulling down</hi> Kings to enlarge the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> of cruſhing <hi>magiſtracy</hi> to nothing, that we might exalt <hi>nothing;</hi> of <hi>depopulating</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> that the <hi>Saints might inherit the earth;</hi> of taking away <hi>all Government,</hi> that we might have the more liberty to <hi>undo</hi> one another; of crying out
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48853:18"/>
againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> that we might have no <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> of chaſing out <hi>Superſtition,</hi> that we might not <hi>ſerve God at all?</hi> They that thought it <hi>idolatry</hi> to <hi>bow</hi> at the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> thought it <hi>none</hi> to <hi>overthrow</hi> all for it, and make every place feel the mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and abuſe, the ſevere and lofty rebukes of <hi>zealous</hi> rage and prophaneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kings</hi> were wont to be lookt upon with more <hi>veneration</hi> and reſpect; and whatſoever account we now-a-dayes make of <hi>them,</hi> yet <hi>God</hi> is ſo careful of their welfare and honour, that he hath ſtrictly charged us not <hi>to touch</hi> or affront them; their <hi>Names,</hi> as well as their <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Calling</hi> are <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, I ſaid ye are Gods,</hi> and if ſo, the very <hi>thought</hi> of <hi>abuſing</hi> them, is <hi>Sacriledge</hi> as well as <hi>Treaſon;</hi> if they are tender <hi>to him as the apple of his eye,</hi> they may well become <hi>precious</hi> in the ſight of <hi>ours. God</hi> made <hi>man</hi> after his own image, but <hi>Kings</hi> have it in a <hi>double</hi> manner: Firſt, as <hi>men;</hi> and then, as <hi>Kings:</hi> by the <hi>one,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent his <hi>Being;</hi> by the <hi>other,</hi> his <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. God</hi> made <hi>man</hi> to <hi>rule inferiour</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48853:18"/>
but <hi>Kings</hi> to <hi>govern men,</hi> and be a more <hi>immediate</hi> copy of his power and glory.</p>
            <p>And truly our <hi>late martyr'd Soveraign</hi> was ſuch an one, the brighteſt <hi>Reſemblance</hi> and repreſentative of his <hi>God</hi> every way, that was upon the earth; <hi>One,</hi> that was <hi>above</hi> others, not more in <hi>place,</hi> than <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>virtue;</hi> not more <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious</hi> for his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> than his <hi>Graces; Crowned</hi> with as much <hi>goodneſs</hi> as <hi>power,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and the <hi>Churches glory;</hi> So eminently <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> from his Youth, that he was thought fitteſt to be the <hi>Churches Angel,</hi> before he became its <hi>nurſing Father;</hi> and more than <hi>Biſhop,</hi> when he was not yet the <hi>Faiths Defender.</hi> And when he came to <hi>govern</hi> both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> did he <hi>change</hi> his temper with his fortune? Was he <hi>leſs</hi> good by being a <hi>King?</hi> No, he was the <hi>Saint</hi> and <hi>Seraphim</hi> of the Throne, his <hi>preſence</hi> was a <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> and every place lookt like a <hi>Temple,</hi> whilſt <hi>he</hi> was there. He never thought himſelf <hi>greater,</hi> than when he was upon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48853:19"/>
               <hi>his knees;</hi> nor <hi>brighter,</hi> than in the <hi>cloud</hi> and incenſe <hi>of his prayers,</hi> throwing his Crown (with the <hi>Elders</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi>) at his feet that gave <hi>it,</hi> and then mingling <hi>himſelf</hi> with thoſe Bleſſed Spirits in adoration and praiſes.</p>
            <p>But beſides his <hi>Piety,</hi> in which he hath outdone all the <hi>Zealots</hi> of his Age, he had all the <hi>virtues</hi> of <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Man;</hi> there were <hi>many</hi> Kings in his time, but none ſo much <hi>after Gods own heart, he</hi> was the true <hi>Majeſty</hi> of his Age. Others might have <hi>larger</hi> Kingdoms, but none ſo <hi>great,</hi> ſo <hi>good a Soul.</hi> Let <hi>ſome</hi> brag of their <hi>mines</hi> and treaſures, and that their Dominions run pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel with the Sun, his <hi>graces</hi> have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done the <hi>one,</hi> and outſhined the <hi>other.</hi> Let <hi>others</hi> boaſt of their <hi>arms</hi> and <hi>banners,</hi> and that that <hi>Lilly</hi> which <hi>exceeded</hi> Solomon <hi>in glory,</hi> is a part of <hi>their Coat,</hi> the Royal and Religious <hi>candour</hi> and integrity of his ſoul, makes <hi>that</hi> look <hi>pale</hi> and fading to <hi>his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> virtue. So great a lover of <hi>peace,</hi> and his <hi>peoples</hi> welfare, that he ſent above <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Meſſages</hi> for <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>ten of them in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48853:19"/>
one year,</hi> in which he hath clearly expreſt, how great and gracious a Soul he had, how <hi>good a Prince,</hi> how excellent a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had <hi>Plato</hi> been alive, he might have ſeen his wiſh, <hi>a Prince and a Philoſopher to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether;</hi> the <hi>Throne</hi> turned into an <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> of Piety and Learning; the <hi>Muſes</hi> and the <hi>Graces</hi> keeping their <hi>Court in him;</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably <hi>skilled</hi> in all <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> but in <hi>Divinity</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Profeſſour;</hi> and his <hi>rare works</hi> ſhew it accordingly: ſuch mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of <hi>Elegancy</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> flowing in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very line, that it is hard to ſay which were <hi>greater,</hi> his <hi>piety</hi> or his <hi>parts;</hi> his <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> or his <hi>faith,</hi> his <hi>Rhetorick</hi> or his <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> the <hi>ſtrains</hi> of his <hi>Fancy,</hi> or the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> of his pious <hi>ſoul;</hi> the <hi>depth</hi> of his <hi>judgment,</hi> or the <hi>humility</hi> of his <hi>mind;</hi> the <hi>excellence</hi> of the <hi>Prince,</hi> or the <hi>Divinity</hi> of the <hi>Saint.</hi> Every thing conſpired to make <hi>him great</hi> and <hi>happy,</hi> but his <hi>graceleſs</hi> and <hi>irreligious ſubjects: Never had people a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter King, never had Prince a more ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhall not <hi>his Fall awaken</hi> us, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48853:20"/>
the <hi>voice</hi> of his <hi>Blood,</hi> ſend us for ſhelter to <hi>his, which ſpeaks better things than that of</hi> Abels: Can ſo <hi>great</hi> a judgment be <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenc't,</hi> but by as <hi>high</hi> and <hi>loud</hi> a repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; a <hi>publick united</hi> ſorrow, and an <hi>univerſal</hi> remorſe. Let <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> thieves and murderers make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their Actions. Let the mad and frantick <hi>Sectary</hi> rave and be deaf, to the voice of ſober reaſon and Religion: but let all that <hi>call</hi> on the Name of Chriſt, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> and <hi>depart from ſo great iniquity,</hi> and abhor the prodigious <hi>Villany</hi> of thoſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that ſhed the <hi>Righteous</hi> and the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al blood:</hi> and whilſt we are <hi>aſhamed</hi> of <hi>them</hi> and <hi>our ſelves,</hi> let us prize the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> of his graces, pay him <hi>Homage</hi> in the <hi>Grave,</hi> and <hi>give</hi> him that tribute of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and obedience we <hi>denyed</hi> him <hi>alive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes <hi>Great Prince</hi> we will <hi>reverence</hi> thy <hi>Memory,</hi> and thy <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> ſhall not be <hi>forgotten,</hi> thy <hi>Sacrifice</hi> ſhall not want <hi>Tears,</hi> nor thy <hi>Martyrdom</hi> a <hi>Trophy,</hi> raiſed by our ſighs; but much <hi>more laſting</hi> and <hi>eternal,</hi> we will <hi>bury thee afreſh</hi> who canſt <hi>never
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48853:20"/>
dye;</hi> nor ſhall <hi>oblivion</hi> ſit upon <hi>thy Tomb</hi> whilſt every <hi>loyal heart</hi> ſhall be thy <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and every <hi>Eye</hi> thy <hi>mourner, every year</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of thy <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> and <hi>our ſhame, thy goodneſs</hi> and <hi>our ingratitude,</hi> thy glorious <hi>piety,</hi> and our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous <hi>diſloyalty.</hi> Thy <hi>Relicts</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſacred,</hi> and thy <hi>name</hi> pretious, thy <hi>ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Canonized,</hi> and thy <hi>death immortal,</hi> the perfume of thy graces, and the fame of thy remains, the voice of thy perfections and never dying piety ſhall be its own <hi>Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> and ſpeaker; Thou haſt <hi>conquered</hi> thine Enemies, and art <hi>entred</hi> into thy <hi>glory,</hi> Triumph't over death, and art ſat down in <hi>greater</hi> Majeſty, and in a <hi>better</hi> Kingdom; and what have <hi>we</hi> to do, but to imitate his piety and goodneſs, and make the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of his life <hi>our</hi> example.</p>
            <p>For though his <hi>Royal Succeſſor</hi> was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly pleaſed <hi>to ſet out an Act of Pardon and Oblivion;</hi> yet <hi>that alone</hi> will not ſerve the turn or <hi>acquit</hi> us of our <hi>guilt;</hi> but we muſt have <hi>Gods pardon</hi> as well as the <hi>Kings,</hi> if we would be <hi>ſecure,</hi> if we would <hi>divert
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48853:21"/>
Gods</hi> judgments for the <hi>future,</hi> and appear with <hi>confidence</hi> and comfort before his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal <hi>hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! how can we expect <hi>Gods</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, when inſtead of <hi>Repenting,</hi> we are ready to <hi>repeat</hi> our ſins, and <hi>renew</hi> thoſe <hi>fatal crimes</hi> that <hi>deſtroy'd</hi> us, willing and forward to <hi>warm</hi> our hands with <hi>new fires,</hi> grow <hi>bright</hi> once more in <hi>Temple flames,</hi> and <hi>conſume</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> with freſh combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions. If this be not ſo, why then is there the noiſe and bleating of <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s calves in every corner, wildfire-doctrine and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious nonſenſe, Scripture perverted to <hi>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> the <hi>Faith</hi> pretended againſt the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel</hi> made uſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Creed.</hi> When there is ſo much <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>prophaneſs</hi> on <hi>one</hi> hand, and <hi>ſchiſm</hi> and <hi>ſedition</hi> on the <hi>other,</hi> and ſo great and <hi>general</hi> a <hi>neglect of God in us all,</hi> can we think our ſelves <hi>ſafe</hi> without ſincere <hi>repentance</hi> and <hi>reformation</hi> of our <hi>ſins;</hi> or that we ſtand <hi>ſo ſecure,</hi> as not <hi>to fall again? God</hi> can <hi>reach</hi> us with a <hi>ſecret</hi> arrow from Heaven, or meet us with an <hi>open</hi> calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48853:21"/>
and judgment in our faces, he can blaſt our pride and confidence in a moment, conſume our ſtrength and beauty in a trice. We have had for many years ſuch a <hi>Viciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitude</hi> of <hi>mercies</hi> and <hi>judgments,</hi> as no Age or Kingdom can parallel, and unleſs we have a mind to be rooted out for ever, from being a people profeſſing his Name, let us make ſuch <hi>timely</hi> ſuitable <hi>returns</hi> and acknowledgements, as may evidence our <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>care;</hi> our <hi>wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>repentance;</hi> our <hi>gratitude</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> under all his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations. Let the <hi>mutability</hi> and <hi>misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes</hi> of <hi>this world, fix</hi> and <hi>ſettle</hi> us the <hi>more on him,</hi> that ſeeing the <hi>uncertainty</hi> and <hi>inconſtancy</hi> of all <hi>earthly</hi> things here <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> we may ſeriouſly <hi>look up,</hi> and <hi>wiſely prepare</hi> for that <hi>glory</hi> which is <hi>above</hi> the <hi>ſtroke</hi> of change or death, that ſo <hi>having fought the good fight, and finiſhed our courſe</hi> with joy, we may have our <hi>warfare crown'd</hi> with <hi>immortality,</hi> and honour, and eternal life among the Saints in light.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
